Guide to The Froebel Society Records: Brooklyn Chapter BCMS.0037
Brooklyn Collection
The Froebel Society Records: Brooklyn Chapter
1891-1957
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0037
1.04 Linear feet in 1 record carton
Minutes, yearbooks and other documents relating to the activities of the Froebel Society, a Brooklyn women's club that promoted cultural activity among its members, who were originally drawn from the mothers of children attending the Froebel Academy.
Related Archival Materials note
Articles about the Froebel Society appearing in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle (1885-1954)
Keep, Mabel Hazlett. Directory of Women in Civic, Economic, and Educational Affairs in Brooklyn Today, 1939: With Original Articles Contributed by a Few Outstanding Women. 1939.
Photographs from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle – Brooklyn Subjects, CBPL 0846, 0847
Historical Note
Friedrich Froebel (1782-1852) was a German educator and founder of the first Kindergarten. His early childhood education philosophy focused on creative play and a close relationship between parents and teachers. In 1850 the Kindergarten was banned by Prussian authorities, but followers of Froebel's philosophies immigrated to Britain where they opened a Kindergarten the following year. The Froebel Society was founded in London in November 1874 to help spread Froebel's ideas and maintain standards for Kindergarten teachers and classrooms.
The Froebel Society operating in Brooklyn was organized in 1884 by mothers of children attending the Froebel Academy. The Academy was located in Bedford-Stuyvesant, first in the home of a teacher and later in Hickock Hall on today's Herbert Von King Park. The Society members were heavily involved with the day-to-day operations of the school, meeting monthly with teachers and working to fundraise and furnish the classroom. Money raised also paid for specialists and guest lecturers invited to speak at Society meetings.
The Society was incorporated on June 12, 1891 for "the advancement of education and educational interests and the promotion of self-culture and mutual helpfulness." As the Academy hired capable, well-educated teachers the Society became less involved with the daily operations of the school and more focused on activities for members. By 1918 the Society had over 80 members, including women without children enrolled in the Academy. Activities such as the Froebel Chorus, Bible study and group discussions on art, literature and politics made the Society an attractive option for progressive Brooklyn women.
By 1955 membership had declined to 37. The remaining members decided to disband the club and donate their materials to the Brooklyn Public Library. The European branch of the Frobel Society merged with the National Froebel Union in 1938 to become the National Froebel Foundation, which dissolved in 1975.
Access
This collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at Brooklyn Public Library's Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
Gift of the Froebel Society, June 1957.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series. Files within each series are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records from the Brooklyn branch of the The Froebel Society, a women's club that promoted cultural activity among its members, who were originally drawn from the mothers of children attending the Froebel Academy.
Series I-IV makes up the bulk of the collection and consists of minutes recording the activities and discussions of various groups active in the Society:
Series I: The Board of Trustees minutes include requests for membership and resignations, matters concerning the Froebel Academy, treasurer's reports, membership dues, payments to florists etc.
Series II: The Business Meeting minutes include votes taken on proposed members and special committee reports. These meetings also included performances, talks, and recitations. Programs of the evening's entertainments are often included with the reports.
Series III: The Records of the Corresponding Secretary list communications sent out to members and correspondence received.
Series IV: Home Committee minutes include records of meetings that took place in the homes of members, who read papers on subjects of interest to the society.
The remainder of the collection includes four yearbooks and a variety of undated notes, speeches and applications.
Froebel Academy; Kindergarten; Women's societies and clubs; Fröbel, Friedrich, 1782-1852
- Series I: Trustees Minutes
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Includes certificate of change in number of trustees, and information on Froebel Society Gift to Brooklyn Public Library dated June 25, 1957.
  - Constitution, By-Laws and Rules, 1923 (June) and 1933 (April) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1904-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1921-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Business Meeting Minutes
  - Minutes of Business Meetings, 1924- 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of Business Meetings, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of Business Meetings, 1945-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Corresponding Secretary Records
  - Records of Corresponding Secretary, 1891-1902 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Records of Corresponding Secretary, 1914-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series 4: Home Committee Minutes
  - Minutes of the Home Committee, 1893-1896 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes of the Home Committee, 1898-1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes of the Home Committee, 1902-1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes of the Home Committee, 1921-1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes Treasurer's annual reports 1928-1929
- Series 5: Year Books
  - Froebel Society Year Books, 1918-1919, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Froebel Society Year Books, 1942-1943, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 6: Notes and Programs
  - Notes for Speeches and a Short Play (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes on the History of the Froebel Society by Mrs. Ronald Taylor, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Celebratory programs (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1, Folder 20)